Guide to the Zambia Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Zambia collection
1929-2011
MS 1550
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.25
(9 boxes)
The collection consists of printed material and photographs relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Zambia.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection (MS 605); Pamphlet Collection (MS 1351); African Postcard Collection (MS 1575). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in this collection is arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed material and photographs relating to political, economic, and social conditions in Zambia.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Mines and mineral resources -- Zambia; Zambia -- Description and travel; Zambia -- Economic conditions; Zambia -- Politics and government; Zambia -- Social conditions; Photographs -- Zambia; Kaunda, Kenneth D. (Kenneth David), 1924-; United National Independence Party (Zambia)
- Original Accession, 1929-1993
  - Papers relating to mining and geological exploration, collected by C. V. Brennan, 1930-1937, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
  - "Reports of Secretaries and Members to Accompany His Excellency the Governor's Address to Legislative Council," government of Northern Rhodesia, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Safari: Special Northern Rhodesia Number, 1954 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Crested Crane: Journal of the Northern Rhodesia Regiment, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Northern Rhodesia (Africa) News Survey", 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - United National Independence Party (UNIP): press statements, policy statements, booklets, printed materials, 1960-1963, 1976, [1981?], undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Independence?: A Framework for Economic Progress in Northern Rhodesia," the Phoenix Group, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Election of 1962: pamphlets, election rolls, tables (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Northern Rhodesia Liberal Party: letters, pamphlets, printed materials, 1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - African National Congress (ANC): election manifestos, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kaunda, Kenneth D., first president of Zambia: speeches, biographies, 1962-1971, 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - News magazines, 1965, [1980?], 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Zambia-The Moulding of a Nation, by Mike Faber, Africa Bureau, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Student/youth organizations: magazines, newsletters, art journals, 1972, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mudenda, E. H. K., Minister of Foreign Affairs: statement to the UN General Assembly, address to the Afro-Arab Committee, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Economic affairs/commerce: booklets, journals, newspapers, [1974?]-1976, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - National Immunization Program: opening address of seminar, 1977 January (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - "The Customary Law of Succession," the Law Development Committee: working paper, 1977 January 9 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Workers' Voice: Official Journal of the Zambia Congress of Trade Unions (ZCTU), 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Lima: a magazine on agriculture; Moog International Cooperation, 1980 December (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Government documents; reports; speeches, 1988-1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - The One Party State and its Future, by Nephas Tembo, Kenneth Kaunda Foundation (KKF), 1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Toward Freedom: A Progressive Perspective on World Events," United States publication, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Newspapers (without political affiliations), 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 25 - 26)
  - Movement for Multi-Party Democracy (MMD): manifesto, [1991?] (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Women for a Healthy Planet: Training of Trainers Workshop," Zambia Alliance of Women, 1993 August 16-23 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs: newsletters, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Travels and Reminiscences of a Native Commissioner in Northern Rhodesia and Tanganyika, Part II - Rhodesia [i.e., Northern Rhodesia], by Jordan E. Knowles, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Federation and Northern Rhodesia: The Facts": a booklet summarizing some of the benefits Northern Rhodesia has obtained from Federation, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - United Federal Party (UFP): policy statement, printed materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "You have been warned": pamphlet against UNIP by unidentified source, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Cooper Exploration of Northern Rhodesia," photographs by Percy W. Donovan, 1929 January 1-July 1 (Box 2, Folder 34 - 35)
  - Photographs by the water: fishing, boating, cooking scenes, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Additional Material, 1938-1996; Accession 1995-M-208
  - Additional printed materials, 1938, 1980-1996, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1937-1995; Accession 2000-M-041
  - Additional printed materials, 1937-1939, 1946, 1949-1956, 1992-1995, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1996-2001; Accession 2002-M-082
  Scope and Contents
  This accession consists of printed materials of Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs).
  - Catholic Commission for Justice and Peace (CCJP), 2000 January-2001 March (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Co-ordinating Committee/ Solidarity for Women's Empowerment in Zambia (NGOCC) [includes scarves], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Foundation for Democratic Process (FODEP), 1996 October-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1997, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1951-2006; Accession 2006-M-030
  - Catholic Commission for Justice and Peace (CCJP), "State of the Nation", 1999, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Catholic Secretariat "The Voice of the Refugees," No. 23, 1988 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Crowder, Michael, University of Zambia History Department, "Lugard and the Amalgamation of Nigeria 1900-1914: A Study in Colonial Diplomacy", 1983 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Election poster, "Vote Heritage", undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Federation of Rhodesia and Nyasaland, Constitution Amendment Act, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Forum for Democracy and Development (FDD), "Contract with the People of Zambia", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Non-Governmental Organizations' Co-ordinating Committee (NGOCC) bulletin, "For Gender and Development", 2002 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Northern Rhodesia "Agreement with the British South African Company on Mineral Rights" Legislative Council Ordinance "Background to the Northern Rhodesia Legislative Council Elections", 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Orbit, The Magazine for Young Zambians," vol 1, vol. 9, no. 1, 1971 Mar, 1985 September-October (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Republic of Zambia Ministry of Mines and Mining Development Annual Report of the Mines Safety Department for 1973 Ministry of Foreign Affairs Annual Report for 1982, 1975, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - United National Independence Party (UNIP) decal, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Zambian Congress of Trade Unions (ZCTU), "Workers' Voice," vol. 2, no. 4, vol. 2, no. 6, vol. 3, no. 2, 1978 December 7, 1979 Jun, 1980 September (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Zango, Zambian Journal of Contemporary Issues," no. 10, 1982 June (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Newsletter (Institute for African Studies, IAS), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Zambian Parliament (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gender Budgets Watch: Cushioning the Vulnerable, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - UDA Presidential Campaign flyers (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Zambia National Women's Lobby flyer (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - MDM parliamentary election flyers (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Examiner, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Additional material, 1952-2011; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed matetrial, 1952-2011 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Posters, Circa 2000s (Folder 3, Box 2, Folder 1)